<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
      <title>Pomodoro on Kevin Sookocheff </title>
      <generator uri="https://hugo.spf13.com">Hugo</generator>
    <link>http://sookocheff.com/tags/pomodoro/index.xml</link>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <author>Kevin Sookocheff</author>
    <copyright>Copyright Kevin Sookocheff.</copyright>
    <updated>Thu, 10 Feb 2011 09:14:23 UTC</updated>
    
    <item>
      <title>Simply Pomodoro for Windows Phone 7 Released</title>
      <link>http://sookocheff.com/posts/2011-02-10-simply-pomodoro-for-windows-phone-7-released</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Feb 2011 09:14:23 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Kevin Sookocheff</author>
      <guid>http://sookocheff.com/posts/2011-02-10-simply-pomodoro-for-windows-phone-7-released</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I just finished my latest application for Windows Phone 7: Simply Pomodoro.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simply Pomodoro provides a simple timer to follow the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pomodorotechnique.com/&#34;&gt;Pomodoro Technique&lt;/a&gt;™ created by Francesco Cirillo. If you don’t know anything about the Pomodoro Technique here’s a quick overview.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pick a task.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Work for 25 minutes. No interruptions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Take a 5 minute break.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Repeat until the task is finished.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It really is that simple! I’ve been using this technique for a while now and although it takes discipline I’ve found that I’m able to maintain sustained productivity throughout the day especially during heavy computer use. Taking periodic breaks to stretch my body and rest my eyes is a simple and effective way to avoid burnout.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are interested, here is the app description and a link to download it yourself!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Simply Pomodoro is a time management technique for getting the most out of your work day. Become more focused, more productive, and more energetic while completing your most important goals. You’ll surprise yourself with how easy it is to become more productive! Based on the Pomodoro Technique™ official website – &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pomodorotechnique.com&#34;&gt;www.pomodorotechnique.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.windowsphone.com/en-gb/store/app/simply-pomodoro/c07d77fd-ac26-e011-854c-00237de2db9e&#34;&gt;Buy it now&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The incredible efficiency of the Pomodoro Technique</title>
      <link>http://sookocheff.com/posts/2010-06-11-the-incredible-efficiency-of-the-pomodoro-technique</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jun 2010 15:09:36 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Kevin Sookocheff</author>
      <guid>http://sookocheff.com/posts/2010-06-11-the-incredible-efficiency-of-the-pomodoro-technique</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I recently started using the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pomodorotechnique.com/&#34;&gt;Pomodore Technique&lt;/a&gt; and am absolutely amazed at home much my productivity has increased.   After one full week I can honestly say I am a convert.  My productivity, and my job satisfaction, has increased knowing that I am making progress towards a goal — each and every day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are not aware of the Pomodoro Technique I will explain it briefly here.  For more information, head over to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pomodorotechnique.com/&#34;&gt;website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Pomodoro Technique can be split into five steps:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Choose a task to be accomplished&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Set the Pomodoro to 25 minutes (the Pomodoro is the timer)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Work on the task until the Pomodoro rings, then put a check on your sheet of paper&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Take a short break (5 minutes is OK)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Every 4 Pomodoros take a longer break&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s it, that’s all.  It really doesn’t get any harder (or easier).  Avoid interruptions and try to be consistent.  Do this for a week and you will be amazed at how much you can accomplish.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>