<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
      <title>Debugging on Kevin Sookocheff </title>
    <link>http://sookocheff.com/tags/debugging/index.xml</link>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Copyright Kevin Sookocheff.</copyright>
    <updated>Tue, 25 Mar 2014 07:23:45 UTC</updated>
    
    <item>
      <title>Stripe checkout opening in a new tab</title>
      <link>http://sookocheff.com/posts/2014-03-25-stripe-checkout-opening-in-a-new-tab</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2014 07:23:45 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Kevin Sookocheff</author>
      <guid>http://sookocheff.com/posts/2014-03-25-stripe-checkout-opening-in-a-new-tab</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;At &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.vendasta.com&#34;&gt;VendAsta&lt;/a&gt; we&amp;rsquo;ve been integrating with the &lt;a href=&#34;http://stripe.com/checkout&#34;&gt;Stripe&lt;/a&gt; payment system using Stripe Checkout. The experience has been completely painless and surprisingly simple. Then came a hiccup. While demoing the new functionality we found that one particular computer in the office would open the checkout modal dialog in a new browser window. Just one laptop. It was running the same version of Chrome that we were developing on. It was running the same OS as a working test machine. But the dialog would consistently open in a new browser window on just this one laptop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a Friday afternoon debugging session our Product Owner decided to jump onto IRC and chat directly with the Stripe developers. They were quickly able to diagnose our problem: touch. The troublesome laptop was a Windows 8 machine with a touch display — and Stripe Checkout will open in a new browser window when used on a tablet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This episode was a great reminder of how the first step in debugging is often to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.hanselman.com/blog/BackToBasicsAssertYourAssumptionsAndDiffYourSourceCode.aspx&#34;&gt;find the difference between the working and non-working system&lt;/a&gt;. Hopefully this post will help someone else with the same problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;P.S. Kudos to Stripe for their prompt help via IRC.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
