<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Kevin Sookocheff</title>
    <link>http://sookocheff.com/tags/html/</link>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Copyright Kevin Sookocheff.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 06 May 2011 10:10:10 UTC</lastBuildDate>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to Display HTML5 Notifications</title>
      <link>http://sookocheff.com/post/javascript/how-to-display-html5-notifications/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 May 2011 10:10:10 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>kevin.sookocheff@gmail.com (Kevin Sookocheff)</author>
      <guid>http://sookocheff.com/post/javascript/how-to-display-html5-notifications/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Chrome recently introduced support for HTML Notifications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the brief tutorial at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.html5rocks.com/tutorials/notifications/quick/&#34;&gt;HTML5 Rocks&lt;/a&gt; I was able to implement this in a matter of minutes and I couldn’t be happier with the results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first step towards implementation is to check if the Notifications API is implemented by the browser. We do this by checking for the existence of the webkitNotifications object.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;// check for notifications support
if (!window.webkitNotifications) {
    alert(&#39;Your browser does not support the Notifications API&#39;);
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a means of preventing unwanted notifications we request permission from the user before displaying anything. The method &lt;code&gt;webkitNotifications.checkPermission()&lt;/code&gt; will return zero if permission has previously been granted. If it returns non-zero we can request permission with the method &lt;code&gt;webkitNotifications.requestPermission()&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;// request permission to use notifications
  if (window.webkitNotifications) {
    if (window.webkitNotifications.checkPermission() &amp;gt; 0) {
            window.webkitNotifications.requestPermission();
    }
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that we have requested permission we can display our notification. We use the function &lt;code&gt;webkitNotifications.createNotification()&lt;/code&gt; to create a Notification object. This function takes three parameters: an icon to display, a title and text. We then call the &lt;code&gt;show()&lt;/code&gt; method on our Notification object to display our notification.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;// display a notification
if (window.webkitNotifications &amp;amp;&amp;amp; window.webkitNotifications.checkPermission() == 0) {
    window.webkitNotifications.createNotification(
        &#39;apple-touch-icon.png&#39;,
        &#39;Awesome!&#39;,
        &amp;quot;You&#39;ve completed a Pomodoro!&amp;quot;).show();
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Notifications specification is currently in Draft format and has been submitted to the HTML working group for standardization. You can see the current spec through the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.chromium.org/developers/design-documents/desktop-notifications/api-specification&#34;&gt;Chromium documentation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The future of mobile development</title>
      <link>http://sookocheff.com/post/mobile/the-future-of-mobile-development/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Jan 2011 09:19:21 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>kevin.sookocheff@gmail.com (Kevin Sookocheff)</author>
      <guid>http://sookocheff.com/post/mobile/the-future-of-mobile-development/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The future of mobile development is cross-platform HTML5, JavaScript, and CSS3.  Let me explain. I’ve been working on a couple Windows Phone 7 applications to accompany my first release, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.appsfuze.com/applications/windowsphone.photo/faceart,3617&#34;&gt;FaceArt&lt;/a&gt;, in the Marketplace. As I do more research and development with the mobile platform I keep looking for ways to increase the reach of my apps. The most obvious is to release Android and iOS versions but I have a few hurdles to clear first, the biggest being lack of time. I do all development as a moonlighting gig while I work full-time and I’m already struggling to find extra hours during the week to finish my first three applications for one platform. How am I going to write and maintain three separate codebases for each app for the major mobile platforms while still keeping my employer happy during the work week?  The solution is cross-platform libraries targeting mobile and web apps. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.phonegap.com&#34;&gt;PhoneGap&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.airplaysdk.com&#34;&gt;AirPlay&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dragonfiresdk.com&#34;&gt;DragonFire SDK&lt;/a&gt; are a few notable products designed for just this problem.  The most notable, and most intriguing for me, is PhoneGap. I first noticed PhoneGap through an article on &lt;a href=&#34;http://arstechnica.com/apple/news/2010/11/introducing-the-ars-technica-reader-for-ipad.ars&#34;&gt;ArsTechnica&lt;/a&gt;. This open-source solution wraps apps designed with HTML5, JavaScript, and CSS in a container suitable for the respective app stores. Why is this exciting? You can design an application for the web and get the mobile app for free (or minimal) time investment.  This is as close to the write once, run anywhere ideal that we will get for mobile phones and as the tools improve the experience is only going to get better for developers.  I personally can’t wait to see what the future holds for this product. What do you think?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
