<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Kevin Sookocheff</title>
    <link>http://sookocheff.com/tags/continuous-delivery/index.xml/</link>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Copyright Kevin Sookocheff.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 23 Apr 2015 08:32:37 CST</lastBuildDate>
    
    <item>
      <title>Continuous Delivery Distilled</title>
      <link>http://sookocheff.com/posts/2015-04-23-continuous-delivery-distilled/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Apr 2015 08:32:37 CST</pubDate>
      <author>kevin.sookocheff@gmail.com (Kevin Sookocheff)</author>
      <guid>http://sookocheff.com/posts/2015-04-23-continuous-delivery-distilled/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/-B0ZEHmBCH8&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What if you could deliver more value, with more speed and with more stability?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What if you could triage bugs faster?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What if you could fix bugs easier and with less user facing impact?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can, with continuous delivery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;toc_0&#34;&gt;Terminology&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, some terminology. What distinguishes continuous integration, continuous
deployment and continuous delivery? Continuous integration revolves around the
continuous automated testing of software whenever change to the software is
made. Continuous deployment is the practice of automatically deploying any
change to the code. Continuous delivery implies that you can deploy any change
to production but for any number of reasons you may choose not to. The focus of
this article is on continuous delivery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;toc_1&#34;&gt;What is continuous delivery?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Continuous delivery is a set of development practices that allow you to release
software to production at any time (&lt;a href=&#34;http://martinfowler.com/bliki/ContinuousDelivery.html&#34; title=&#34;Continuous Delivery&#34;&gt;Fowler, 2014&lt;/a&gt;). By following
these practices you can reduce the cost, development time and risk  of
delivering features to users (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.thoughtworks.com/insights/blog/case-continuous-delivery&#34; title=&#34;The Case for Continuous Delivery&#34;&gt;Humble, 2014&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s expand upon these definitions by talking about what differentiates
continuous delivery from traditional software development. With continuous
delivery, at any point in time any stakeholder in the business can ask for the
current version of the software to be deployed to production. This implies that
your software is deployable throughout the development lifecycle and that the
development team prioritizes keeping the software stable and deployable over
working on new features (&lt;a href=&#34;http://martinfowler.com/bliki/ContinuousDelivery.html&#34; title=&#34;Continuous Delivery&#34;&gt;Fowler, 2014&lt;/a&gt;). It also implies some level
of testing and deployment automation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following diagram of the continuous delivery process helps to visualize the
automation steps that typically accompany a software change and the subsequent
release of the software to production. The red bars in the diagram signal that
failures at this stage of the process halt the entire process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, the delivery team or development team makes a change and commits that
change to a version control system. This check in triggers automated unit tests
that verify the commit. If those unit tests pass, automated acceptance tests run
and if those pass we move on to manual user testing. Once the user has tested
and approved the change a release can go out. From a development standpoint it
is important to understand that any code commit that passes testing may be
released to customers at &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; point in time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;thumbnail&#34; href=&#34;http://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Continuous_Delivery_process_diagram.png#/media/File:Continuous_Delivery_process_diagram.png&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/7/74/Continuous_Delivery_process_diagram.png&#34; alt=&#34;Continuous Delivery process diagram - Jez Humble&#34;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;toc_2&#34;&gt;Why Continuous Delivery?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Google, Facebook, LinkedIn, Netflix, Etsy, Ebay, Github and Hewlett-Packard,
among many others, have adopted continuous delivery in their products. On
average, Amazon makes changes to production code every 11.6 seconds
(&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=dxk8b9rSKOo&#34; title=&#34;Velocity Culture&#34;&gt;Jenkins, 2011&lt;/a&gt;) &amp;ndash; that&amp;rsquo;s 3000 production deployments every
day. Facebook commits to master 5000 times a day deploys to production twice
a day (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.infoq.com/presentations/Facebook-Release-Process&#34; title=&#34;The Facebook Release Process&#34;&gt;Rossi, 2011&lt;/a&gt;). Etsy deploys more than 50 times a day
(&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.infoq.com/news/2014/03/etsy-deploy-50-times-a-day&#34; title=&#34;How Etsy Deploys More Than 50 Times a Day&#34;&gt;Miranda, 2014&lt;/a&gt;). Why would companies do this? What is the
benefit?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_3&#34;&gt;Reduced Risk&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first benefit is reduced risk. Each deployment is a smaller change that can
easily be understood in isolation. If an error occurs it is trivially easy to
roll-back a single change or push a new release on top of the change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_4&#34;&gt;Believable Progress&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Developers are generally quite bad at estimating software delivery projects
([Milstein, 2013][Milstein2103]). If the definition of &amp;ldquo;done&amp;rdquo; means &amp;ldquo;developers
declare it to be done&amp;rdquo; that is much less believable than if it&amp;rsquo;s safely deployed
into a production environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_5&#34;&gt;Faster Iteration Towards Product Fit&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Generally speaking, the biggest risk in software development is building
something that the user doesn&amp;rsquo;t want. Continuous delivery is a great enabler of
A/B testing and allows you to frequently get working software in front of real
users to assess user behaviour and performance impact of software changes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_6&#34;&gt;Expose Inefficiencies&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Continuous delivery enforces discipline on the software development team to
always keep the product in deployable condition. This discipline naturally
exposes inefficiencies in the development process &amp;ndash; anything that gets in the
way of the goal of releasing working software quickly is an impediment to
development that will quickly be brought to light with continuous delivery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_7&#34;&gt;Encourage Responsibility&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With continuous delivery, the developer making a change and the developer
deploying the code is the same person. This avoids any problems with handing
your deployment &amp;lsquo;over the wall&amp;rsquo; and allowing another person or team to test,
deploy and verify the code. It keeps the onus on working software with the
people most knowledge about how the software works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;toc_8&#34;&gt;Does Continuous Delivery Actually Work?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rather than reflect on a few abstract benefits, let&amp;rsquo;s look at some of the
available data on continuous delivery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ThoughtWorks (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.thoughtworks.com/insights/blog/case-continuous-delivery&#34; title=&#34;The Case for Continuous Delivery&#34;&gt;Humble, 2014&lt;/a&gt;) analyzed their data on high performing
companies and found that those practicing continuous delivery ship code 30 times
faster, have 50% fewer failed deployments, and restore service 12 times faster
than their peers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In A Practical Approach to Large-Scale Agile Development (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.ca/Practical-Approach-Large-Scale-Agile-Development/dp/0321821726&#34; title=&#34;A Practical Approach to Large-Scale Agile Development: How HP Transformed LaserJet FutureSmart Firmware&#34;&gt;Gruver,
2012&lt;/a&gt;). Hewlett-Packard, who had been practicing more traditional
software delivery process, experimented with continuous deployment in an
organization having roughly 400 developers working over 3 continents. After
switching to continuous delivery, they integrated small changesets over 100
times a day and deployed at least ten times a day. What happened? The number
of features under active development increased by 140% and development costs
per feature reduced by 78%. This amounted to a total development cost
reduction of 40%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;toc_9&#34;&gt;How to do Continuous Delivery?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, you may be sold on the benefits of continuous delivery and are
asking how to get started. Continuous delivery requires a few components to be
effective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;toc_10&#34;&gt;1. Continuous Integration&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A build server performing continuous intergration of every commit is a
necessity. Once a code change is committed, the build server triggers the
testing and deployment pipeline ultimately leading to successfully deploying a
production release.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;toc_11&#34;&gt;2. Automated Testing&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Automated unit testing, and, where applicable, automated performance testing,
makes it easy to spot issues in code about to be deployed. If any of
these tests fail the current release is rejected. This is not a silver
bullet. Manual QA is still needed to verify a build and test before
releasing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;toc_12&#34;&gt;3. Feature Flags&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some features are too big to commit as one chunk. In these cases a &lt;a href=&#34;http://martinfowler.com/bliki/FeatureToggle.html&#34;&gt;feature
flag&lt;/a&gt; is used to hide
functionality that is not ready for general release, while still allowing code
to be released to production.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;toc_13&#34;&gt;4. Monitoring&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Monitoring systems allow the development and test teams to easily see the effect
a given change has on user behaviour, system performance or system stability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;toc_14&#34;&gt;5. &amp;ldquo;One-Click&amp;rdquo; Deployment and Roll-Back.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deployments and roll-backs must be easy enough for anyone to do at a moments
notice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;toc_15&#34;&gt;Continuous Delivery in Practice&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s run through three examples of how continuous delivery would look like in
practice, contrasting continuous delivery with a more traditional release
process. In these examples, the traditional release process assumes that any
changes scheduled to be released are held in a development environment for one
week, a staging environment for one week, and finally deployed to a production
environment after one week on the staging environment. Each envrionment
corresponds to a unique code branch (develop, test, master) and weekly merges
take place to push the development code up to the test branch (and staging
environment) and the test code up to the master branch (and production
environment).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;thumbnail&#34; href=&#34;/img/2015-04-23-continuous-delivery-distilled/continuous-delivery-in-practice.png&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;/img/2015-04-23-continuous-delivery-distilled/continuous-delivery-in-practice.png&#34; alt=&#34;Traditional Release Structure&#34;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_16&#34;&gt;Scenario 1: Bug Fix&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine a scenario where a customer reports a bug in the system. The bug is
simple enough for a single developer to work on and the fix is small enough to
understand within a single code commit. Let&amp;rsquo;s begin by examining the traditional
release process to see how this bug fix reaches the customer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The developer, Brad, begins by checking out the latest copy of the development
branch, and begins work on the bug. Once he is confident that the bug has been
fixed he goes over the changes with QA and merges the bug into the develop
branch where it waits for the weekly deployment to test.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;thumbnail&#34; href=&#34;/img/2015-04-23-continuous-delivery-distilled/bug-fix-stage-1.png&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;/img/2015-04-23-continuous-delivery-distilled/bug-fix-stage-1.png&#34; alt=&#34;Merging to Develop&#34;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brad is now free to pick up another issue and commit the code for that issue to
develop, where it waits once again for the weekly deployment to test. Test now
has two issues that have been committed to development that will be released to
the test environment in one week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;thumbnail&#34; href=&#34;/img/2015-04-23-continuous-delivery-distilled/bug-fix-stage-2.png&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;/img/2015-04-23-continuous-delivery-distilled/bug-fix-stage-2.png&#34; alt=&#34;Second Merge to Develop&#34;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, other developers are working on issues and committing the code to
develop. By the time the weekly deployment to the testing environment comes
around we end up with 13 disparate issues being pushed to the test environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;thumbnail&#34; href=&#34;/img/2015-04-23-continuous-delivery-distilled/bug-fix-stage-3.png&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;/img/2015-04-23-continuous-delivery-distilled/bug-fix-stage-3.png&#34; alt=&#34;Group of Merges to Develop&#34;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, the QA team can perform regression testing of all of these 13 issues for
the week that this release is held in the test environment for staging. After
one week has passed, the test branch is merged with the master branch and a
deployment to production is done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;thumbnail&#34; href=&#34;/img/2015-04-23-continuous-delivery-distilled/bug-fix-stage-4.png&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;/img/2015-04-23-continuous-delivery-distilled/bug-fix-stage-4.png&#34; alt=&#34;Group of Merges to Develop&#34;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s also important to note that &lt;em&gt;we still do not know that the bug fix will
address the customer&amp;rsquo;s issues on production&lt;/em&gt;. We can&amp;rsquo;t know for sure that the
bug fix not complete until it fixes the issue on the production environment. So,
after the release a prudent developer will check back to make sure the bug
is no longer an issue and it can be marked as resolved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point we delivered the bug fix to the customer after a two week waiting
period. We also dedicated testing time to this bug fix before merging it to the
development branch, to regression test the release in the staging environment,
and to test this bug fix on the production environment. For
arguments sake, let&amp;rsquo;s say this testing time took 1 hour on each
environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;toc_17&#34;&gt;Total Customer Time Waiting For This Bug Fix:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2 weeks&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;toc_18&#34;&gt;Total Testing Time:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3 hours&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now imagine we have 13 issues that have been delivered with this release, we can
compound the total waiting time and total testing time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;toc_19&#34;&gt;Total Customer Time Waiting For This Release:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;26 weeks&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;toc_20&#34;&gt;Total Testing Time For This Release:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;39 hours&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s contrast this with a continuous delivery approach. In this scenario, Alice
works on an issue by first checking out the latest production code from the
master branch. Once she is confident she has fixed the bug and it has passed QA,
she merges the bug in to the master branch and deploys the fix to
production. Let&amp;rsquo;s assume that she took two hours to fix the bug and that
the bug required one hour of testing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;toc_21&#34;&gt;Total Customer Time Waiting For This Release:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2 hours&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;toc_22&#34;&gt;Total Testing Time For This Release:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1 hour&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can compound this by assuming we have 13 issues that are being worked on for the week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;toc_23&#34;&gt;Total Customer Time Waiting For This Week:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;26 hours&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;toc_24&#34;&gt;Total Testing Time For This Week:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;13 hours&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_25&#34;&gt;Scenario 2: Regressions and Rollback&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now imagine that the bug fix in the scenario above actually causes a regression
on production that needs to be fixed immediately or rolled back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Brad&amp;rsquo;s case (the weekly release process), someone on the devops or change
management team packages the production release and pushes it to the production
environment. And something goes wrong. Devops knows that one of 13 different
change sets have been released but have no way of knowing which of those change
sets is causing the regression. A critical issue is created identifying the
problem and this issue is handed off to the development team. The team works to
triage the issue, notices that Brad&amp;rsquo;s change caused the problem and Brad is now
in charge of fixing it. But the last time Brad worked on this piece of code was
two weeks ago and his memory is a bit fuzzy about why the change was made. Or
maybe Brad is on holiday and someone else needs to pick up his work without
fully understanding the intricacies and risks involved with the chage.
Ultimately, the team decides they can&amp;rsquo;t go forward and all 13 change sets are
rolled back until they can properly fix the problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;thumbnail&#34; href=&#34;/img/2015-04-23-continuous-delivery-distilled/weekly-regression.png&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;/img/2015-04-23-continuous-delivery-distilled/weekly-regression.png&#34; alt=&#34;Regression in Weekly Release&#34;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contrast this with a continuous delivery approach. Alice works with QA to verify
her change. Alice and QA deploy the change to production and immediately verify
that the integrity of the fix. And something goes wrong. In this case, there is
only one change set that could have cause the problem &amp;ndash; Alice&amp;rsquo;s. Alice has
immediate knowledge of the changes she just committed and possible reasons for a
failure. She can choose at this point to fix the issue and release her fix or to
roll-back her single change. In this scenario, Alice is responsible for the
integrity of her changes and for verifying that her work was done correctly. She
is able to work in concert with QA to test the issue and does not simply push
her issue &amp;lsquo;over the wall&amp;rsquo; for someone else to test and deploy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;thumbnail&#34; href=&#34;/img/2015-04-23-continuous-delivery-distilled/continuous-regression.png&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;/img/2015-04-23-continuous-delivery-distilled/continuous-regression.png&#34; alt=&#34;Regression With Continuous Delivery&#34;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With continuous delivery, each deployment is a smaller change that can be easily
understood, fixed or, when necessary, rolled-back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_26&#34;&gt;Scenario 3: New Features&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;ve seen how continuous delivery can aid in deploying bug fixes, but what
about delivery new features? Remember that with continuous delivery any commit
at any time can be deployed directly to the production environment. So how can
you deploy partially complete features? The answer is &lt;a href=&#34;http://martinfowler.com/bliki/FeatureToggle.html&#34;&gt;feature
flags&lt;/a&gt;. Feature flags allow
the developer to write a new feature or edit an existing feature without
exposing those changes to the end user.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a brand new feature, it&amp;rsquo;s relatively easy to develop the entire feature
behind a feature flag that is inaccessible to the user by not exposing the new
page, button or widget at all. Once the feature matures it can be opened up to
QA or product managers for testing and eventually rolled out to a small
percentage of users. These users are able to test the feature with real
production data and real production load &amp;ndash; making sure everything works as
expected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gradually rolling out the feature also gives you the ability to &lt;em&gt;measure user
behaviour&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;gather feedback&lt;/em&gt; before committing to a certain path of action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When enhancing existing features or doing refactoring, feature flags work best
with continuous delivery when following a &lt;a href=&#34;http://martinfowler.com/bliki/ParallelChange.html&#34;&gt;parallel
change&lt;/a&gt; design pattern, where
both the old and the new code is run during a request, but only one version of
the result is returned to the user. As a concrete example, imagine we are trying
to improve the performance of a page through a refactoring. When a request comes
in, we route the request to both the old and new code and can measure &amp;ndash; on
production &amp;ndash; the performance of the new code. We can easily see if our proposed
refactoring has measurable performance improvements in a real-world setting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;thumbnail&#34; href=&#34;/img/2015-04-23-continuous-delivery-distilled/parallel-code.png&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;/img/2015-04-23-continuous-delivery-distilled/parallel-code.png&#34; alt=&#34;Parallel Code&#34;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, by extracting performance measurements over each iteration of the
code we visually compare the effect of a code change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;thumbnail&#34; href=&#34;/img/2015-04-23-continuous-delivery-distilled/performance-comparison.png&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;/img/2015-04-23-continuous-delivery-distilled/performance-comparison.png&#34; alt=&#34;Performance Comparison&#34;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can also use the same pattern to ensure we have confidence in the results of
our new code. For example, on each request, we can run both the old and the new
code, and compare the results on real-world production data. When we are
confident that the differences between the new and old code are within an
acceptable error range the new code is ready to go live. We also have the
ability to use production data to inform our unit tests and guard against future
regressions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;thumbnail&#34; href=&#34;/img/2015-04-23-continuous-delivery-distilled/accuracy-comparison.png&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;/img/2015-04-23-continuous-delivery-distilled/accuracy-comparison.png&#34; alt=&#34;Accuracy Comparison&#34;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Caution must be exercised whenever using feature flags. Every feature flag that
is in use within the product is technical debt that should be short lived.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;toc_27&#34;&gt;Towards Continuous Delivery&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Continuous delivery is not a panacea &amp;ndash; it requires diligence and responsibility
on behalf of the development team. However, if the team is able to cross these
hurdles continuous delivery can be used to deliver stable software to customers
faster than ever before.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
